const ATTRIBUTE_1E = '1E';
const ATTRIBUTE_2E = '2E';
const ATTRIBUTE_SPELL = 'spell';
const ATTRIBUTE_RACE = 'race';
const ATTRIBUTE_CLASS = 'class';
const ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON = 'weapon';

const SUBSTITUDES = [
    ['elf', 'elves'],
    ['dwarf', 'dwarves'],
    ['multiclass', 'multi-class'],
    ['dualclass', 'dual-class'],
    ['player\'s handbook', 'players handbook', 'phb'],
    ['dungeon master\'s guide', 'dungeon master guide', 'dmg'],
];

const DRAGON_MAGAZINES = [];
DRAGON_MAGAZINES.push({
    publication_year: '1989',
    publication_month: 'August',
    issue_number: '148',
    foreword: `And now, for a special edition of Sage Advice! The AD&D® 2nd Edition game has arrived, and the sage is here with an in-depth look at the 2nd Edition *Player's Handbook*. All page numbers herein refer to the 2nd Edition text alone, unless otherwise stated.`,
    sage_advice: [
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How long does a *produce flame* spell last? How many flames can the caster hurl?`,
            answer: `*Produce flame* lasts one round per caster level. The caster can throw a maximum of one flame per level, but no more than one flame per round.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How do you determine how many square feet of *faerie fire* is required to cover a creature?`,
            answer: `Just assume the caster can cover one man-size creature per level. Assume small creatures equal one-half a man, and large creatures equal one-and-a-half men.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can halflings become clerics? Also, where are the advancement limits for demihuman characters?`,
            answer: `Yes, halflings can become clerics. See the upcoming 2nd Edition *Dungeon Master's Guide* (page 15) for advancement limits for halfling clerics and other demihuman characters.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_RACE, ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can a thief character take the mountaineering proficiency and improve his climbing chance?`,
            answer: `Yes, but the character's climbing chance cannot be made better than 95%.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Are you supposed to multiply strength bonuses to damage in a successful backstab, as described on page 40, or are you supposed to add strength bonuses after the multiplier, as explained on page 104?`,
            answer: `The text on page 104 is correct.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `What penalties does a bard suffer by using thief abilities when wearing normal chain mail?`,
            answer: `Use the Elven Chain column in Table 29 but add another - 5% to the column's values.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Are multiclassed bards allowed? The text on page 45 mentions multi-classed bards, but the chart on page 44 does not.`,
            answer: `Page 44 is correct; page 45 is wrong.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `According to page 13, any warrior with a strength score of 16 or more gets a 10% bonus to experience. But later on, in the descriptions of the paladin and ranger, the rules say that members of these classes must have other high ability scores to get the bonus. Which is correct?`,
            answer: `The text on page 13 is a misprint. Fighters get the 10% for a strength score of 16 or better; paladins and rangers must have additional high ability scores.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `What happened to the fighter's ability to double specialize with a weapon?`,
            answer: `It has been dropped.`,
            comment: `Reintroduced by Player's Option: Combat & Tactics`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can a fighter specialize with more than one weapon?`,
            answer: `No, but he can "save" additional slots as he earns them and specialize with a weapon later in his career if he doesn't fill those slots at the start.`,
            comment: `Added in The Complete Fighter's Handbook`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Do demihuman fighters get to roll for extraordinary strength?`,
            answer: `Yes; all warrior characters are entitled to exceptional strength rolls if they have strength scores of 18.`,
            comment: `Halflings to not roll for exceptional strength. Corrected in Sage Advice #`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10+12',
            question: `Does armor interfere with the new ranger's *animal empathy* ability? What is that ability's range? Why don't druids have this ability?`,
            answer: `A ranger can wear any type of armor and still use *animal empathy*. The ranger must be close enough to the animal to attract the animals undivided attention (about 10 yards in a wilderness setting less, if the setting is something like a crowded marketplace that provides distractions). Individual DMs may give druids *animal empathy* if they wish. The rules don't give the druid this ability because a druids focus is on nature as a whole, not just on animals.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Isn't the new ranger too limited in spells? Can a ranger pick more than one type of creature for an enemy?`,
            answer: `The ranger's two spheres give him plenty of spells. However, individual DMs might want to add a sphere or two; one campaign I am familiar with allows rangers to use healing spells. The DM has to decide what constitutes a valid enemy. Since the rules mention giants, it is probably acceptable to choose a class of creatures. Thus, a ranger from the FORGOTTEN REALMS™ setting might be allowed to choose the goblin races (see *Cyclopedia of the Realms*, page 46) as an enemy. A ranger can never choose two or more entirely different creatures as enemies.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Can rangers wear elven chain mail and still use the special abilities described on page 28?`,
            answer: `Elven chain mail interferes with a ranger's special abilities; refer to Table 29 (page 39) for a list of penalties. Elven chain mail also negates the ranger's ability to use two weapons without penalty.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Does the ranger's + 4 attack bonus vs. a specific type of adversary apply to both attack and damage rolls?`,
            answer: `The bonus applies only to attack rolls; see page 29.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Can paladins become dual-classed characters?`,
            answer: `As clearly stated on page 44, there are no restrictions on the class combinations allowed to dual-classed characters, provided that alignment restrictions are respected. Most DMs, however, do not allow characters to combine subclasses (e.g., no bard/thieves, paladin/rangers, etc.).`,
            comment: `Revised Player's Handbook (black book) made it a hard rule that you cannot dual/multi-class in the same group. The Complete Bard's Handbook reintroduced it for bard multi-classes.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `With the large increase in the number of wizard spells, why wasn't there an increase in the minimum and maximum number of spells a wizard can learn? A wizard with an 18 intelligence can learn a maximum of 18 spells a level; that's less than half the number of first-level spells!`,
            answer: `The AD&D® game is one of choices. The additional spells are intended to create a greater variety of mage characters, not more powerful mages.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Table 22 (page 31) shows the minimum ability scores required for specialist wizards. What is the minimum intelligence score required for a specialist wizard?`,
            answer: `Specialist wizards must have an intelligence score of at least 9, just like a normal wizard.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What happened to the write spell?`,
            answer: `It isn't needed anymore. The primary function of the write spell was to allow a mage to add a spell to his books after he had failed his chance to know roll for that spell. In the 2nd Edition game, a mage can attempt a new chance to know roll each time he gains a new level. (See "Spelling It Out," in DRAGON® issue #147, for more information.)`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What is the material component for the *spectral hand* spell?`,
            answer: `There is none. The "M" in the components' line is a typographical error.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Does casting the first version of a *flame arrow* spell break invisibility?`,
            answer: `No, because this is not an attack.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Does the *delayed blast fireball* spell have a damage limit?`,
            answer: `Yes. The limit is l0d6 + 10 hp damage.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Several spells are missing from Appendix 5.`,
            answer: `Here are the schools for the omitted spells (at least the ones I know about): *irritation deafness*, *fabricate* and *slow* are alteration spells (*fabricate* is also an enchantment); *Melf's minute meteors*, evocation and alteration; *locate object* and *know alignment*, divination; *geas*, enchantment/charm.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `In Table 22 (page 31), the races allowed entry for diviners is any. Does this mean that a character of any PC race can be a diviner?`,
            answer: `No. Only races eligible for the mage class (humans, elves, and half elves) can become diviners.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What happened to cantrips?`,
            answer: `Cantrips are still in the game. Just use the first-level *cantrip* spell. If you need help figuring out what kind of cantrips to cast, use your copy of *Unearthed Arcana* as a guide. Actually, things are better now for cantrip-using mages because they no longer need to waste spell book space on cantrips, and they are no longer limited to the few cantrips in their books.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Since mages start the game with the ability to read spell books and to write in them, do they also have the ability to read and write their native languages?`,
            answer: `No. Magic is written in a special language.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `The new rules mention the possibility of *fireballs* detonating early and *lightning bolts* rebounding because of hitting an obstruction. My group and I thought these spells always hit, just as a *magic missile* spell does. If these spell do not always hit, how does the mage hit his opponent?`,
            answer: `The spells do always hit, after a fashion. In the case of a *fireball*, the missile bursts at the designated range unless it strikes an object before it gets there. Since the missile flies in a straight line between the caster and the target, it can be blocked by invisible barriers (such as *walls of force*) or by a bend in a passage obscured by an illusion or mirror.\nA *lightning bolt* is similar to a *fireball* in that the spell begins at a designated height and range, extending directly away from the caster. A *lightning bolt* is always either 40' or 80' long, and the caster must decide which when he casts the spell. If caster miscalculates and casts this spell into an area too small to contain it, the lightning bolt grows to its full length (as measured from the point where it strikes a barrier), heading back at the caster unless it smashes through the barrier (see page 151). Some readers have misread the example on page 151; *lightning bolts* do not bend or fold over when hitting a barrier. The 80' bolt in the example starts 40' away from the caster, travels 10', and strikes a barrier; the bolt must maintain its full length, however, so the opposite end of the bolt (starting from the point of origin) instantly grows out in the direction toward the spell-caster, extending 70' from its point of origin. Thus, the bolt's final length is SO'. A victim caught between the point of origin and the wall behind him is not struck twice by the bolt. The use of the word rebound in the spell's description seems to be the confusing element.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_SPELL],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `The text under the new *identify* spell says a fully charged *ring of three wishes* radiates only faint magic. Is this an error?`,
            answer: `There is no error in the spell's description, but you have made an erroneous statement. The *identify* spell does not detect magic or its strength; it reveals an item's functions and charges. A *ring of three wishes* has only three charges, so it is faintly charged. Smart wizards use a *detect magic* spell, which can determine magical strength and type, before casting *identify*.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
    ],
});
DRAGON_MAGAZINES.push({
    publication_year: '1989',
    publication_month: 'September',
    issue_number: '149',
    foreword: `We present part two of our special edition of "Sage Advice" (continued from DRAGON issue #148), with an in-depth look at the AD&D® 2nd Edition *Player’s Handbook*. All page numbers herein refer to the 2nd Edition text alone, unless otherwise stated.`,
    sage_advice: [
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Does a character need to spend two proficiencies in bastard sword use—one for one-handed use and one for two-handed use?`,
            answer: `This is up to the DM, but I suggest that two slots be required. One campaign I am familiar with allows characters with long sword or two-handed sword proficiency to use the bastard sword in its corresponding mode (in other words, a character who can use a long sword can use a bastard sword one-handed without penalty).`,
            comment: `The Complete Fighter's Handbook suggest indicates that only 1 proficiency slot is needed`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How can a sling bullet do the same damage as a heavy crossbow and more damage than a light or hand crossbow? Why would anyone bother with a crossbow when a sling has a better rate of fire, the same or better damage, a lower cost, and a lower weight?`,
            answer: `Slings are very effective weapons and are often underrated. The bullets are heavy, have excellent aerodynamic qualities, and are hurled with a great deal of force. Why doesn't everybody use a sling? Well, try to swing a sling underwater, while hiding in dense undergrowth, or from around a corner. Also, bow and crossbow specialists get a point-blank range category and the ability to fire before the initiative roll in some cases.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `The new rules (on page 106) say a character must make a system shock roll to be raised from the dead. If so, what are resurrection survival scores used for?`,
            answer: `This is a typographical error. System shock rolls are made when characters are exposed to magical aging, polymorphing, or petrification. Resurrection survival rolls are used when bringing slain characters to life again.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How much does a wooden staff cost?`,
            answer: `Any character can cut and trim his own staff. Prepared staves cost 1 sp each.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can characters use missile weapons when fighting toe-to-toe with an opponent?`,
            answer: `Characters cannot aim and fire bows, use slings, or hurl hand-held weapons while in melee. Loaded and cocked crossbows can be fired in melee but cannot be reloaded. Since light and heavy crossbows are too large to be very handy, the DM might rule that they can be fired only when the user has initiative.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How much damage does an arrow fired from a short bow do? Can flight or sheaf arrows be fired from short bows?`,
            answer: `Short bow arrows do 1-6 hp damage to targets of all sizes. No matter what sort of arrow is fired from a short bow, it does damage as a flight arrow (1d6/1d6).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `The charging rules say that a spear set vs. a charge does double damage, but this in not mentioned in the equipment list.`,
            answer: `Any weapon that can be set vs. a charge does double damage when so employed.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can a character attack while with- drawing?`,
            answer: `This is up to the DM, but I suggest not. If you do allow fighting withdrawals, the character making the withdrawal should get an attack only if there is an opponent following him. Even then, the character should attack last and with a -2 penalty to his attack roll.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10+12',
            question: `The rules mention nets, lassos, and mauls as possible weapons for clerics (page 34), but these weapons do not appear in the weapons charts (pages 68-69).`,
            answer: `A maul is a warhammer; see the Weapons Table on pages 68-69. Lassos and nets are not part of the 2nd Edition game and were mentioned in error. However, a typical war net is made from woven hemp cords and has small lead weights sewn into the edges. It is 5' across, weighs 6 lbs., and costs 12 sp. It takes two hands and 6' of clear space to throw a net, and the effective range is 30'. Any target hit by the net must save vs. breath weapon or become entangled. Entangled victims cannot fight or move, and defend at -2. Entangled victims wriggle free if they make a successful wrestling attack vs. AC 2; they can make one attempt to get free each round. When used as a melee weapon, treat a net as a scourge. A lasso is simply a rope with an adjustable loop. A successful hit with a lasso puts the loop around part of the target creature's body, but this does not necessarily immobilize the creature; the DM has to decide where the loop is (around the neck, a limb, the upper body, etc.) and assess the appropriate penalty. Since the lasso's wielder can pull the loop tight, the only way to escape, short of killing the wielder or getting the rope away from him, is to cut or break the rope.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `A broad sword is mentioned as a thief's weapon (page 38), but the broad sword is not described.`,
            answer: `Use these statistics for that weapon: cost 10 gp; weight 4 lbs.; size M; type S; speed factor 5; damage 2d4 (S-M)/1d6 + 1 (L).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What is the rate of fire for a high-level fighter using an arquebus?`,
            answer: `The rate of fire for any missile weapon stays the same for all users regardless of level, except for specialized users (see Table 35, page 52).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `How can a character become proficient with an arquebus? Wouldn't this require a large or even unlimited supply of powder and shot? If the character chooses to specialize, what would the rate of fire be?`,
            answer: `This is up to the DM, but your suggestion regarding gunpowder supplies sounds reasonable because the character would have to practice with the weapon. Arquebus specialists rates of fire are: 1st-6th level, 1/3; 7th-12th level, 1⁄2; 13th level and up, 1/1.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Can a fighter attack with a long sword in each hand?`,
            answer: `No; two-weapon attacks are limited to one medium and one small weapon, or to two small weapons.`,
            comment: `This was added in The Complete Fighter's Handbook with Two-weapon style specialization.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Can a fighter who is specialized with two weapons use them both at the same time and get the damage bonus and multiple attacks for each hand? Does a fighter get a strength bonus for each hand?`,
            answer: `Fighters can specialize with only one weapon. Any character attacking with two weapons gets one—and only one—extra attack per round; the character gets the full number of attacks for the primary weapon and one attack from the secondary weapon. The DM can allow strength bonuses for each hand, but I do not recommend it. Limit strength bonuses to one weapon or the other, or allow the character to split the bonus between weapons.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `How large are light crossbow quarrels and short swords?`,
            answer: `Light quarrels and short swords are small weapons. To preserve game balance, you might want to disallow the use of short swords as secondary weapons in two-handed attacks.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What happened to weapons' space requirements?`,
            answer: `Space required for melee weapons can be inferred from their sizes and types. Bludgeoning or slashing weapons generally require as much clear space for use as their lengths. Piercing weapons and most missile weapons generally require 1' of clear space.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Why can't blunt melee weapons be used in nonlethal combat? It seems to me that a weapon like a mace would be better for knocking out a creature than a sword would be.`,
            answer: `As explained on page 98, a mace has no "flat" side that can be used at less than full effect. Still, since using a weapon in nonlethal combat carries a -4 attack roll penalty, you could assume that the mace wielder could "pull the blow" and inflict reduced, temporary damage.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_WEAPON],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `On page 101, the section on saving-throw priority says Table 60 is set up in order of priority. But the example given contradicts this.`,
            answer: `Table 60 is correct; the example is wrong.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What is the conversion rate be- tween the 1st Edition monetary system and the 2nd Edition monetary system?`,
            answer: `The new system is close enough to the old one so that you need not convert treasures or prices. (Prices in the 2nd Edition game tend to be higher, but this reflects adjustments in the relative values of some items, not a decline in the value of currency.) The only real difference is that silver and copper pieces have doubled in value with respect to gold (compare page 35 of the 1st Edition *Players Handbook* with page 66 of the 2nd Edition *Player's Handbook*). If you are a stickler, cut the number of copper and silver coins in any 1st Edition module's horde by half to reflect the new values of those coins.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `When setting prices for items not listed in the 2nd Edition game, what is the conversion rate between U.S. dollars and gold pieces?`,
            answer: `An AD&D game gold piece is worth approximately $20 when comparing buying power. Note that if a group of AD&D game adventurers found themselves in a modern setting, their gold pieces would be next to worthless as legal tender, but very valuable for their gold content.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Can the various subclasses be used in multiclassed combinations (e.g., a half-elf ranger/thief, or an elf mage/bard)?`,
            answer: `No; only the classes listed on page 44 can be used in multiclassed combinations.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Do multiclassed characters still divide their experience points among classes?`,
            answer: `Yes; see page 44.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_CLASS],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `When a character temporarily loses one point of constitution from long-distance swimming, does he also lose bonus hit points gained from that point of constitution?`,
            answer: `Yes; any constitution loss strips bonus hit points gained from the lost points. Temporary constitution losses thus produce temporary hit-point losses.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What happened to weapons' space requirements?`,
            answer: `Space required for melee weapons can be inferred from their sizes and types. Bludgeoning or slashing weapons generally require as much clear space for use as their lengths. Piercing weapons and most missile weapons generally require 1' of clear space.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Are alignment languages used?`,
            answer: `Alignment languages are not part of the 2nd Edition game.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `Do drow and deep gnome PCs still have the abilities attributed to them in *Unearthed Arcana*?`,
            answer: `All subraces in the 2nd Edition game are treated just like members of the appropriate main race. However, individual DMs are free to retain *Unearthed Arcana* attributes for drow and deep gnomes.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What are the size classes of each of the PC races?`,
            answer: `Halflings, dwarves, and gnomes are small creatures. Humans, half-elves, and elves are medium (man-size) creatures.`,
            comment: `Dwarves are generally considered man-sized when handling weapons, i.e. a dwarf can carry a M-sized weapon in 1 hand. This is corrected in Sage Advice #174`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What happened to weapons' space requirements?`,
            answer: `Space required for melee weapons can be inferred from their sizes and types. Bludgeoning or slashing weapons generally require as much clear space for use as their lengths. Piercing weapons and most missile weapons generally require 1' of clear space.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '12',
            question: `What good is the healing proficiency if a character can regain the hit points just by resting for a day?`,
            answer: `First, the healing proficiency restores lost hit points to characters who do not or cannot spend an entire day resting. Second, the two forms of healing are cumulative, so that a character who rests an entire day and receives treatment from a character with healing skill regains 1d3 + 3 hp/day. Note that a character who tends wounded characters is not considered to be resting.`,
            comment: `The bonus healing from the Healing proficiency is a flat rate of 1,2 or 3 (with Herbalism). The random 1d3 healing is for immediate care after someone has taken damage.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `According to Table 65 (page 122), unskilled characters have a base climbing chance of 40%. The same table notes that a character who spends one slot for the mountaineering proficiency also has a 40% climbing chance. Is this an error, or do characters have to spend two slots before they are better climbers than unskilled characters?`,
            answer: `Yes, there is an error. The base climbing chance improves 10% for each slot spent on mountaineering; thus, a character with one proficiency slot in this skill has a 50% base climbing chance.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `According to Table 67 (page 123), it is impossible to climb a "dry" ice wall, but a character can climb a slippery ice wall at one-fourth the normal climbing rate. Is this an error?`,
            answer: `This is not really an error. All ice walls qualify as slippery surfaces—there are no dry or slightly slippery ice walls.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Chapter 7 says a character can try to disbelieve an illusion just by spending a round doing so. Furthermore, if the player can give a good reason why the character is disbelieving, the DM can give a bonus to the saving throw. But Appendix 2 says a reason must be given for any disbelief attempt to succeed. Which is correct?`,
            answer: `Chapter 7 is correct. Appendix 2 is intended to remind players that disbelief is never automatic; disbelief must be active. In other words, do not check for disbelief unless a player says his character is disbelieving; if the character has a very good reason to disbelieve and if the player can explain this reason to the DM; a bonus to the disbelief roll might be awarded. The text in Appendix 2 is also intended to convey to players that they cannot avoid illusions by having their characters disbelieve everything that comes along. The DM need not quiz the player about the exact reasons for disbelief, but the DM should be convinced that the character has some legitimate reason for disbelieving an illusion before he allows a saving throw.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Do full and field plate armor still absorb damage?`,
            answer: `No, they don't.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `What good is a helmet? Does any suit of armor come with one?`,
            answer: `Helmets protect the head and are important to any character with a humanoid body. Every suit of armor is assumed to include a helmet whose construction is similar to the armor. If an armored character wears no helmet, he loses one armor class (for example, AC 4 becomes AC 5).`,
            comment: `Further expansions on the rules for helmets are in The Complete Fighter's Handbook and Player's Option: Combat & Tactics`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `I was shocked to see that TSR, Inc. condones the killing of baby drag- ons (as graphically illustrated by the color plate on page 7).`,
            answer: `With the new information on dragons given in the first *Monstrous Compendium* (TSR product #2102), available in July, PCs are going to have to catch dragons while they are small if they are going to have any chance to kill them at all (see also "The New Ecology of the Dragons," in DRAGON issue #146, for more information).`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `If the proficiency system is used, do demihuman characters have to spend a slot to learn the common tongue since they begin with their native tongue only?`,
            answer: `Strictly speaking, demihumans must spend a slot to know Common. However, DMs should feel free to give Common to demihuman characters for "free." It can be fun to role-play characters who cannot speak with each other, but this kind of play can bog down the game and usually gets boring after a few sessions.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Can the running nonweapon proficiency be used with the jogging/running rule? Are the two cumulative?`,
            answer: `A character using the running proficiency cannot use the jogging rule (he is already moving as quickly as the jogging rule allows). He can, however, use the running rule to increase his speed. If the character fails one of the ability checks for continued running, he must follow the rules on page 120, and has finished using his running proficiency for the day.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `According to Table 65 (page 122), unskilled characters have a base climbing chance of 40%. The same table notes that a character who spends one slot for the mountaineering proficiency also has a 40% climbing chance. Is this an error, or do characters have to spend two slots before they are better climbers than unskilled characters?`,
            answer: `Yes, there is an error. The base climbing chance improves 10% for each slot spent on mountaineering; thus, a character with one proficiency slot in this skill has a 50% base climbing chance.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Page 45 says a dual-classed character who loses a level to an energy drainer will lose his highest level; if drained again, he loses the level that is hardest to replace. However, the example shows a character losing one level in each class to a wight. What is the correct procedure?`,
            answer: `A dual-classed (or multiclassed) character who loses a single level to an energy drain always loses his highest level, no matter how many times he is drained. If his levels are equal, he loses the level that takes the most experience to regain. The example on page 45 is correct only if the character loses two levels at once. In this case, the dual-classed character loses one level from each class, just as in the 1st Edition AD&D game.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `I thought falling damage was cumulative per 10', reaching 20d6 at 60'. What happened?`,
            answer: `The controversy over falling damage has been settled. Falling damage is 1d6 for each 10' (or fraction of 10') fallen. The reasons are thoroughly explained on page 104. Individual DMs are free to plague their players with any variant falling damage systems they can devise.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Does a character take falling damage if he deliberately jumps?`,
            answer: `In most cases, yes. If the DM wants to simulate short jumps, I suggest calling for a dexterity check. If the check succeeds, subtract 10' from the jump's height—that is, a 10' jump inflicts no damage, a 20' jump inflicts 1d6, and so on. Failure results in a normal fall.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '13',
            question: `Are the nonweapon proficiency modifiers shown in Table 37 (page 54) applied to the die roll or to the ability score?`,
            answer: `The adjustments are made to the character's ability score.`,
            attributes: [],
        },
    ]
});
DRAGON_MAGAZINES.push({
    publication_year: '1989',
    publication_month: 'October',
    issue_number: '150',
    foreword: `Combat and melee in the AD&D® 1st Edition game make up this month's topic, with special advice on fighting hydras. All references to the *Dungeon Masters Guide* and *Players Handbook* in this article are to the 1st Edition versions of those volumes. In all cases, the information in the AD&D 2nd Edition volumes takes precedence where there is a contradiction between those rules and this column.\nBut first, a special word from the sage, then one from the editor.`,
    sage_advice: [
        {
            page_number: '8',
            question: `Why haven't you answered my 27 letters, each with 57 questions on my favorite game system? You said you would reply if I sent an SASE with each letter. Why don't you give a seminar at the GEN CON® game fair? If I come to Lake Geneva, can I meet you and ask you questions?`,
            answer: `Although the "Sage Advice" in DRAGON issue #121 said the sage would make personal replies, I receive so many letters that I cannot answer every one. (However, if you don't enclose an SASE, I cannot reply at all.) Usually I reply only to letters that have questions I can use in the column, so that all the readers get the benefit of my time. Needless to say, I don't give extended private interviews in Lake Geneva or anywhere else.\nIf you want to increase your chances of getting a personal reply, do the following:\n1. Look through your books for your answers, and be sure to consult the indexes (if the books have them). Often, with a little extra effort, you'll find rules that have eluded you.\n2. Keep your letter short. Decide what you really need to know, and stick to the most important questions. As I've stressed before, role-playing games involve choices and decisions; don't be afraid to make some on your own.\n3. Include the title of the book and the page number that contains the rule you are asking about; this saves me a lot of page flipping.\nMy work with the RPGA™ Network keeps me busy at almost every game convention I attend, and seminars are not the best place to answer rules questions. I'm not an encyclopedia of game knowledge. I rely on a big library and a large network of personal contacts to find answers, and few people would be entertained by watching me flip through my books and consult my files while I struggle with a tricky question. Still, I do answer some questions at conventions; just keep them short, and don't interrupt me while I'm running a game. Also, some conventions I attend collect written questions for me so that I can use them in the column or work on them during the show and discuss the results with anyone who is interested.\nSkip Williams`,
            attributes: [],
        },
        {
            page_number: '8',
            question: `Why are you still running questions for the AD&D 1st Edition game now that the AD&D 2nd Edition game is on the market?`,
            answer: `DRAGON Magazine will continue to use material specifically for the AD&D 1st Edition game simply because so many people use that edition. The 2nd Edition has only been out for six months, but the 1st Edition game has been available for over a decade. (Remember, too, that material for one edition can usually be used with the other with ease.) As time goes on, we expect that more players will switch to the 2nd Edition game, and our coverage of that system will increase. We want to offer the most useful material to the largest number of gamers.\nRoger E. Moore`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '8-9',
            question: `What is the proper way to handle a fight with a hydra? Does the creature's effective hit dice drop as it loses heads? Will damage to the creature's body kill it? How do area-effect spells such as *fireball* effect the heads? How does one determine when a lernaean hydra's regeneration ability is stopped?`,
            answer: `Hydras do pose a few problems, especially when magic is involved. I suggest the following rules for handling combat with a hydra.\nA hydra's effective hit dice do not drop as the creature loses heads. With respect to melee, each of a hydra's heads is treated as a separate creature. Each head dies when it reaches zero hit points, and excess damage does not carry over to another head. When all heads are reduced to zero hit points, the creature dies immediately. Hits to a hydra's body will kill it; the body has as many hit points as the total hit points of its starting heads. When the body is reduced to zero hit points, however, the creature continues to fight as long as it has at least one living head. It will then fight for an additional 2-8 rounds or until the body is reduced to -20 hp.\nA lernaean hydra's regeneration ability makes it a tougher nut to crack. The individual heads can be slain in the normal manner; however, a fire source must be applied to each slain head or it will regenerate. *Burning hands* is the easiest way to scorch the stumps or sundered heads. A torch, flask of oil,. or *flame tongue* sword will stop a single head's regeneration if applied in time. Any successful hit on the slain head will stop regeneration. A lernaean hydra stays alive as long as it has one living or regenerating head (hits to the creature's body not withstanding).\nWhen any hydra is affected by an area spell such as *fireball* or *lightning bolt*, the heads are treated as a single entities, with the damage distributed as evenly as possible among the heads. Although the heads are separate melee targets, they are still part of the same creature. The creature's body suffers as much damage as the heads took in total (i.e., the hydra gets one saving throw, but the heads and the body each take damage).\nSpells that can kill a creature outright such as *death spell*, *power word kill*, or *disintegrate* kill the creature only if it fails its saving throw (if applicable). When determining a hydra's resistance to such spells, its effective hit dice are equal to its starting number of heads (or peak number, in the case of a lernaean hydra), and its effective hit points are equal to the total hit points of all the heads (damage to the body notwithstanding).\nA spell that affects one creature or a limited area (such as *magic missile* or *burning hands*) must be directed either at the body or at one or more heads of the hydra, according to the limitations of the spell. Spells such as *charm monster*, *hold monster*; or *slow* affect the entire creature, as the beast effectively has only one brain—perhaps at the base of the necks inside the body.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What happens if a magic-user uses a sword when in desperate need?`,
            answer: `If a character's need is truly great, the DM can allow any class of character to use a weapon prohibited to his class. The normal nonproficiency penalty applies (perhaps with an additional - 1 to hit). If a player falls into the habit of declaring his characters in desperate need too often, however, the DM should either disallow the use of the prohibited weapon or give the character no experience award for completing the adventure.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What are the effects of blindness and deafness on spell-casting?`,
            answer: `Blinded creatures are unable to cast any spell that requires a target, but spells that can be cast on an area (such as *fireball*) or delivered by touch (such as *cure light wounds*) may still be used. Deafness can cause spells with verbal components to be miscast and fail. The failure chance is up to you, but it shouldn't exceed 20% (less for spells with short casting times). The cleric spell *holy word* has a deafness effect that causes spells to fail 50% of the time; this is due mostly to the extreme power of the holy word, not merely the deafness.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What is the significance of weapon speed factors?`,
            answer: `Weapon speed factors allow for comparison among weapons. The lower the speed factor, the quicker the weapon. Their most common use (and the only use mentioned in the rules) is for breaking ties on initiative. When a tie occurs, compare weapon speed factors; the lowest factor goes first. However, on the first round of a melee, when the opponents are closing, the longer weapons have the advantage. The advantage is also with mounted opponents attacking or defending against unmounted opponents and with characters who are defending or attacking from above. Spellcasting time is equivalent to the weapon speed factor. That is, a weapon with a speed factor of 3 is as slow as a three- segment spell for purposes of tie breaking.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `How do you use the weapon to-hit adjustment tables in the *Players Handbook* (page 38) and *Unearthed Arcana* (page 27)? I don't understand what they mean.`,
            answer: `The tables list the bonus or penalty given to a weapon against the basic armor types. For example, the line for Axe, Hand reads: -5, -4, -3, etc., for AC 0, AC 1, AC 2, etc., respectively. Full plate armor and shield gives AC 0, so a hand axe has a -5 to hit vs. full plate armor and shield. If the target were wearing full plate armor + 1 and using no shield, the adjustment is still AC 0. However, full plate armor alone is AC 1, so you use the AC 1 column regardless of magical bonuses, and the hand axe has a -4 to hit. The same holds true for dexterity bonuses. These tables are for attacking humans, demi-humans, and humanoids—never for attacking monsters. Use of the tables is strictly optional; they were included in the game mainly to satisfy the real history buffs who know that certain weapons were much more effective than others on the medieval battlefield.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What do the following weapons look like: bardiche, spetum, voulge, guisarme, halberd, and scimitar?`,
            answer: `Some of the less-known weapons in the AD&D game are pictured and described in *Unearthed Arcana*, pages 123-128. The weapons depicted on these pages include everything on your list except the scimitar. A scimitar is simply a curved broad sword used by Arabs and Saracens. If you've seen any movies depicting the Middle East during the crusades, you've seen scimitars.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What is a morning star?`,
            answer: `A morning star looks like a long, thin club with spikes or flanges at the business end. The morning star in the AD&D game is similar to a mace but is longer and heavier. Some books on weapons identify a ball and chain as a morning star, but this combination is considered to be a flail in the AD&D game.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `Why did *Unearthed Arcana* take shields away from assassins? It seems a high price to pay for the option of having a good alignment.`,
            answer: `*Unearthed Arcana* is in error. Assassins may use shields but not during a melee round in which the character is engaged in the act of assassination. The alignment expansion was not an error.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `Can a character with a girdle of giant strength throw a halberd? When one of my players tried to do this I allowed it, but with a big to-hit penalty.`,
            answer: `You were correct. Pole arms are not intended to be thrown, no matter what the thrower's strength. Anything, however, can be thrown with some chance of success. For throwing a pole arm, we suggest a to-hit penalty of -4 at short range (10' or less), -6 at medium range (11-20'), and -9 at long range (21-30'). We also suggest that you use these ranges outdoors where other missiles have ranges measured in yards. A pole arm is far too long for a human-sized creature to throw like a hand axe (so that the weapon spins or tumbles), no matter how much strength is available. Spear-type throws are possible, but hits can inflict damage only if the pole arm that is thrown has a spear point. Use spear damage (1-6) in this case, not pole-arm damage.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What are the effects of total dark- ness on combat? When last faced with this problem, I simply ruled that everything within the darkness was invisible, and I applied the -4 to-hit penalty.`,
            answer: `You handled the situation correctly. More information on the effects of darkness is given on page 32 of the *Dungeoneer's Survival Guide*.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `What does the space requirement listed for each weapon mean?`,
            answer: `The space requirement is exactly that: the minimum space a character must have in order to use a weapon. For example, a fighter must be standing in a space at least 4' wide to use a battle axe. Space requirements are cumulative; therefore, two fighters using battle axes side-by-side would require 8' of space.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9',
            question: `Can creatures with at-will abilities use such abilities while attacking? Can they use several abilities in the same round, say one per segment?`,
            answer: `Creatures that have at-will abilities may use one such ability, once per round, in addition to normal movement or attacks.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '9-10',
            question: `Can magic-users move during a round when they cast spells?`,
            answer: `A magic-user must remain stationary only as long as the casting time of the spell. After casting a spell, the mage can move during the remainder of the round. For example, a *fireball* takes three segments; therefore, the mage casting it could have seven segments worth of movement after casting the spell. See page 102 of the *Players Handbook* for per-segment movement rates.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Is it possible for a character to leave a melee without exposing his back?`,
            answer: `The DM might allow a character to back out of a melee at half speed so that the opponent's free attack would be frontal. Some campaigns allow a friendly character to cover for a retreating character so that the extra attack is resolved normally against the the character who is covering.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can fighters with multiple attacks attack more than one opponent per round?`,
            answer: `Yes; so can monsters and the members of other character classes that get multiple attacks.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `How long does paralyzation last? Is it permanent until cured? What cures paralyzation? What is paralyzation, really?`,
            answer: `In medical terms, paralyzation is the loss of sensation in part of the body as the victim's brain, for one reason or another, no longer controls the body. The uncontrolled muscles relax, and the victim goes limp. Autonomic muscles, such as the heart and lungs, are unaffected. Some kinds of paralysis in the AD&D game (paralysis caused by ghouls and ghasts, for example) cause the victim to become rigid and immobile. In either case, paralysis affects only the body, not the mind. The victim can still think and use psionics or any form of movement that does not require muscular effort. For example, if a character becomes paralyzed while using a *fly* spell, he can still fly until the spell runs out.\nParalyzation is not permanent. It can last anywhere from several rounds or turns to as much as a day. It can be removed with a *remove paralysis* spell (which removes paralysis of all types) or by a *cure disease*, *neutralize poison*, or *dispel magic* spell, depending on what caused the paralysis. Paralysis caused by undead creatures is disease- or fear-based; paralysis caused by living creatures is poison-based; paralysis caused by a *glyph of warding* or the illusionist spell *paralyzation* is magic-based. The AD&D 2nd Edition *Monstrous Compendium*, Volume 1, lists the duration for ghoul paralysis as 3-8 rounds and ghast paralysis as 5-10 rounds. Paralysis caused by more powerful creatures lasts longer; lich paralysis, for example, lasts until dispelled.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E, ATTRIBUTE_2E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `Can a character with a bastard-sword proficiency also use long swords and two-handed swords, or does the character instead, require a proficiency in both long and two-handed swords?`,
            answer: `Each weapon on the weapons lists requires a separate proficiency Although a bastard sword can be used one-handed with the same effect as a long sword, its larger size requires different handling. Likewise, the bastard sword requires different handling than the longer and heavier two-handed sword. However, if a character is proficient in bastard sword, he may use that sword either way.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `What is a bastard sword's space requirement and speed factor when used one-handed?`,
            answer: `The same as when it is used two-handed.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10',
            question: `If a fighter is specialized (or double specialized) in a bastard sword, does he get the specialization bonuses when using the sword two-handed and one-handed?`,
            answer: `A bastard sword is primarily a two-handed weapon. For purposes of game balance, it is best to limit specialization bonuses to two-handed use (or let the player choose).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '10+36',
            question: `When a character gains proficiency with a multipurpose weapon (such as a kusari-gama in Oriental Adventures), does the character automatically gain proficiency with the weapons that correspond with each function (in this case, with chain and kama)?`,
            answer: `The situation is analogous to that of the bastard sword described previously. Knowledge of the combination weapon does not necessarily allow use of its component weapons. The techniques required to use each of the weapons you mentioned are different. The governing principle in both of these cases is the no-free-lunch rule: You can't get two or more proficiencies for the price of one simply by selecting a multipurpose weapon.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `When do charging characters attack? What are the effects of a charge?`,
            answer: `Charging monsters or characters may attack normally at the end of their charge; exactly when depends on the reach of the weapons being used (longer weapons attack first). The charge movement, initiative, and affects chance to hit. See the *DMG*, page 66, for more details on charging.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `How do high dexterity scores or a *short sword of quickness* affect initiative?`,
            answer: `High dexterity never affects initiative; it affects only surprise. A *short sword of quickness* allows the wielder to attack first. This is not the same has having the initiative; a thief-acrobat (for example) cannot automatically evade each round simply because he has a *short sword of quickness*. He must win the die roll before he can evade.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `Can missile weapons, other than hurled melee weapons, he used in melee?`,
            answer: `No, missiles cannot be fired or hurled when the firing character is in melee. Furthermore, bows and arrows are not melee weapons and cannot normally be used in hand-to-hand combat. A bow or crossbow could, however, be used for pummeling (see *Unearthed Arcana*, page 107).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `Can a character fire a missile into a melee without hitting friendly characters? If not, what is the chance of hitting an ally?`,
            answer: `This depends on the situation. When firing into a melee, use the following procedure:\nThe character firing the missile declares which creature he is targeting. (Any of the character's allies who are fighting with the target creatures are potential targets for the missile.) Randomly determine which target will actually be in the path of the missile. If the figures in the melee are about the same size (e.g., human vs. hu- man, elf vs. dwarf), there is an equal chance that either the enemy or an ally could be the missile's actual target. If the die roll indicates that an ally will be the actual target and there are multiple allies fighting the intended target, randomly determine which ally is the actual target.\nRoll the to-hit number. If the appropriate number for the target's armor class is rolled, then the target is hit whether or not the character firing the missile wanted to hit that target. If the creatures in the melee are of different sizes, the larger creatures are more likely to be hit. I sug- gest a two-thirds chance (1-4 on 1d61 to hit the larger target when the height difference is 2-3' (ignore height differences of less than 2'). If the height difference is more than 3', allow the missile to hit the larger target automatically if the firer wishes; otherwise, the chance to hit the larger target is 5 in 6.\nMany campaigns exempt the *magic missiles* spell from this rule. *Magic missiles* are assumed to unerringly strike their targets.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `Is it possible to use an object for nonlethal combat? How much dam- age would a chair or bar stool do?`,
            answer: `Yes, you can use odd objects for nonlethal combat. The amount of damage such objects can do depends on their hardness and mass. See *Unearthed Arcana*, page 107.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `How far can objects be tossed or thrown?`,
            answer: `The maximum range for any tossed object is 5" (a stone) or 3" (a flask of oil or a vial of holy water), as long as the object is reasonably compact. Large, bulky objects have a maximum range of 2" or less, depending on the situation.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36',
            question: `How do you handle gaze attacks?`,
            answer: `A creature with a gaze weapon may use it on one opponent per round in addition to any physical attacks. If the creature is unintelligent, this will be a random opponent. Intelligent creatures may pick their victims. Any opponent who can see the creature can be subject to the attack. The opponent who is subjected to the gaze attack must save vs. petrification. Some campaigns allow opponents to avert their eyes and become immune to the gaze attack, but such opponents attack and defend at a -4 penalty, and the decision to avert the eyes must be made prior to both the initiative roll and anyone knowing where the gaze will be directed. Some DMs may rule that if an entire party is surprised, all must save against the gaze during the first surprise segment of the encounter (several party members could accidentally meet the creature's gaze during the confusion of the surprise segment).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '36+38',
            question: `I seem to recall some rule about a penalty when a character makes more than one attack in a round. Is there such a rule?`,
            answer: `We can refer to page 70 of the *DMG* for this answer. The reference states that a character may use a second weapon instead of a shield, provided that the second weapon is a dagger or hand axe. Otherwise, there is no penalty for multiple attacks.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `Is there any way to prevent a *vorpal weapon* from severing the neck if the attack roll is high enough?`,
            answer: `No. However, the DM might choose to introduce some kind of protective magic that would do this. Note the limitations given on page 166 of the *DMG*. The DM might choose to introduce some additional limitations; for example, it would be impossible for a human to sever a cloud giant's neck unless the giant was bent over or the human was flying or levitating.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `Will unholy water harm a paladin?`,
            answer: `Yes. It is created by an evil ritual and is harmful to paladins and good creatures of extraplanar origin such as devas and solars.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `Can a cleric turn undead, then attack, run away, or cast a spell in the same round? Or does he stand there for a whole round, give up shield and dexterity adjustments to armor class, and hope that the turning works?`,
            answer: `Turning undead is a separate activity. A cleric who turns undead may not fire missiles, melee, or cast spells in the same round as he turns undead, although he defends normally and may be able to move (DM's option).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `The monk ability *quivering palm* does not work on creatures that are struck only by magical weapons. Looking at the *DMG*, I see that creatures that are themselves immune to normal weapons can hit other creatures that are immune to nor- mal weapons. Does the reverse hold true? That is to say, are those creatures that can hit creatures immune to normal weapons immune to normal weapons themselves? Specifically, are high-level barbarians immune to normal weapons and *quivering palm*?`,
            answer: `The barbarian's ability to hit those creatures that are normally hit only by magic weapons does not protect him from nonmagical weapons or a monks *quivering palm*.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `Can a torch be used as a weapon? How far can a torch be thrown? There are some instances when it is desirable to use a torch as a second- ary weapon; is this allowed?`,
            answer: `Torches can be used as primary weapons; treat them as clubs for all purposes—even when throwing and inflicting damage, assuming that the torch is lit and the target is not immune to fire. A torch may be used as a secondary weapon if the DM thinks the situation warrants it. Apply the "Attacks With Two Weapons" rule on page 70 of the *DMG*. If players attempt to abuse the privilege, the DM might have a character set fire to himself or his equipment. Have the torch either save vs. normal blow as thin wood, or break. The fire has a 10% chance of going out per blow.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `How long does it take to draw a weapon?`,
            answer: `Any weapon can be drawn in one segment (this effectively adds one segment to the weapon's speed factor). Common sense, however, dictates that a character who draws a weapon during a melee will lose initiative to a character who has already drawn his weapon, unless the character with the drawn weapon must use the segment that is required for the draw in order to close to melee range. Note that sheathing a weapon takes a bit longer; changing weapons carefully takes a full round (see *Oriental Adventures*, page 54).`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38-39',
            question: `How come a low-level character gets only one attack per round? A one-minute melee round certainly allows time for several attacks, especially if the character uses a light weapon such as a dagger.`,
            answer: `A single melee attack in the AD&D game **assumes** the exchange of several blows. The player's single attack roll represents the result of a series of attacks by the character, not just a Single blow. See the *DMG*, page 61, for more details. High-level characters who are allowed multiple attacks do not actually strike more blows; their greater experience merely allows them to strike a larger percentage of *telling* blows.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '39',
            question: `*Unearthed Arcana* (page 78) says that a sap will stun an opponent if it hits him in the head when the head is uncovered. Since there are no hit location tables in the AD&D game, how do you determine if the sap hit the opponent's head?`,
            answer: `The *DMG* has a rule that says an intelligent creature can aim a blow at an opponent's head half the time (1-3 on 1d6). While this rule (see page 46) encourages characters to wear helmets, I think it's a bit excessive. Try any of the following for adjudicating attacks with a sap:\nAny attack roll four or more over the minimum score needed to hit the target strikes the head. Strength bonuses don't count when determining the minimum score to hit, but bonuses for rear attacks (including a thief's back-attack bonus) and attacks on prone opponents do count.\nTreat the sap as a pummeling implement, and use the rules on page 107 of *Unearthed Arcana*. The sap does no damage unless a stun is scored. It has the chance of a large and hard object to stun, and does normal sap damage (1-2) when a stun is scored. A sap is a weapon and negates the initiative penalty for pummeling attacks. Roll a 1d6 before each attack; a one indicates that the attack will strike the head if the sap hits.`,
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
        {
            page_number: '38',
            question: `The *DMG* gives a procedure on page 70 for attacking magically sleeping opponents, but what about normally sleeping opponents?`,
            answer: `The to-hit bonus vs. normally sleeping opponents is +4.`,
            comment: 'This clarification is what have been left out in 2E and is what is referenced in Sage Advice #265',
            attributes: [ATTRIBUTE_1E],
        },
    ]
});

module.exports = DRAGON_MAGAZINES;